<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Løvenskiold_stattholderrapporter_1844-1856</title>
            <editor>Mette Ekker</editor>
            <author/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2016-11-23</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>no publication statement available</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p/>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <name>meek</name>
               <date>2016-11-23</date>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="rapport">
            <head>
               <supplied resp="editor">Christiania 6. februar 1848</supplied>
            </head>
            <div type="hoveddel">
               <head type="sub">Underdanigst Rapport!</head>
               <p>	Min sidste underdanigste Rapport var af 20de forrige Maaned.</p>
               <p>	Posten bragte mig den 3die denne Maaned Deres Majestæts naadige <lb/>
Skrivelse af 31te forrige Maaned, tilligemed Deres Majestæts naadige <lb/>
Befaling om Storthingets Aabning, Throntalen og Meddelelsen om Rigets <lb/>
Tilstand.</p>
               <p>	Den 1ste denne Maaned samledes Storthingets Medlemmer for at <lb/>
revidere Representanternes Fuldmagter og at iværksætte de sædvanlige <lb/>
Forberedelser til dets Aabning, hvorunder Stiftamtmand Falsen fører <lb/>
Præsidiet. Det eneste mærkelige, som herunder er forefalden, er, at  <lb/>
Fuldmagtscomitéen har forkastet Statsrevisor Daa's Valg i Søndre-Bergenhuus <lb/>
Amt, fordi han ikke kan ansees som dets Indvaaner, som uden Tvivl imorgen <lb/>
vil blive bifaldt af Storthinget. Jeg beklager i flere Henseender, <lb/>
at næste Storthing skal savne Daa, som afgiver et nyt Beviis paa, at <lb/>
Folkegunst, saakaldt Popularitet, er kortvarig.</p>
               <p>	Vedlagt tillader jeg mig underdanigst at vedlægge en Fortegnelse <lb/>
over Storthingets Medlemmer, hvoraf en hæderlig Mand beklageligviis er <lb/>
udgaaet, nemlig Oberstlieutenant Sommerschild, Representant for  <lb/>
Trondhjems Bye, der paa Reisen hertil er afgaaet ved Døden paa Urskoug <lb/>
Præstegaard, 5 Mile herfra.</p>
               <p>	Jeg venter, at Storthinget vil anmelde sig constitueret Tirsdag den <lb/>
8de, i hvilket Fald jeg agter at iværksætte dets Aabning Onsdag den <lb/>
9de denne Maaned.</p>
               <p>	Da Stiftsgaardens Locale vil blive mere end optaget Storthingets <lb/>
Aabningsdag ved at modtage og beværte over 150 Personer, har jeg funden <lb/>
mig nødsaget til at udbede de 2de store Sale og Hjørneværelset i det <lb/>
Kongelige Palais indrømmet til Samling for Processionen og til Modtagelse <lb/>
af Storthingets Deputation, som jeg smigrer mig med, at Deres Majestæt <lb/>
naadigst vil bifalde.</p>
               <p>	Paa Grund af Gjenstandens Vigtighed tillader jeg mig underdanigst at <lb/>
vedlægge Copie af Hr Stephensons Forslag om de Vilkaar, hvorpaa vort <lb/>
projecterede Jernbaneanlæg imellem Christiania og Mjøsen kan ventes <lb/>
overtaget af et engelsk Actieselskab samt hans originale Brev til mig om <lb/>
samme Gjenstand, som jeg underdanigst tør bede naadigst remitteret. Jeg har <lb/>
endnu ikke havt Anledning til at omtale Sagen med nogen Sagkyndig eller <lb/>
til at overveie den selv tilstrækkelig; men ved første Øiekast forekomme <lb/>
de fremsatte Vilkaar mig saa byrdefulde og uantagelige, at det maa være <lb/>
tilraadeligere at iværksætte den hele store Sag for Statens egen  <lb/>
Regning.</p>
               <p>	Deres Majestæt vil uden Tvivl allerede have erfaret, at det har <lb/>
behaget Gud at hjemkalde vor ældste og dygtigste Biskop Dr Neumann, i <lb/>
hvem Deres Majestæt og Staten har tabt en udmærket og troe Tjener.</p>
               <p>	Af hosfølgende fra Understøttelsesselskabet for Trængende, vil <lb/>
naadigst erfares, hvorledes Deres Majestæts Naadegave sidstleden 26de  <lb/>
Januar er bleven taknemmelig anvendt.</p>
               <p>	Med Hensyn paa Generaladjutant Kroghs underdanigst vedlagte yderligere <lb/>
Oplysninger om de 2de naadigst omskrevne forafskedigede Overconstabler, <lb/>
tillader jeg mig underdanigst at foreslaae, at Deres Majestæt naadigst <lb/>
vil skjænke Peder Nielsen en Gratification af 10 à 15 Speciedaler <lb/>
og Hans Olsen en aarlig Pension, lig den han nyder af Krigshospitalscassen <lb/>
9 3/5 Spdl. aarlig, eller en naadigst Gratification af 15 à 20 Speciedaler <lb/>
een Gang for alle.</p>
               <p>	Min Søn Ernst, som tilbringer nogle Dage her, for at assistere <lb/>
General Wedel og mig ved Storthingets Aabning beder sig lagt for Deres <lb/>
Majestæts Fødder. <lb/>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <placeName>Christiania</placeName>
                     <date>den 6te Februar 1848. </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <lb/>
Til <lb/>
Hans Majestæt Kongen <lb/>
                  <salute>underdanigst		</salute>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Løvenskiold</persName>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="vedlegg">
               <head type="tillegg">
                  <supplied resp="editor">Tillegg til rapport av 6. februar 1848</supplied>
               </head>
               <opener>	Deres Excellence<lb/>
    	  Norges Rigs Statholder Løvenskiold!<lb/>
        	  Ridder og Commandeur af Hs Majestæts Ordener. –</opener>
               <p>	Administrationen giver sig herved den Ære at indberette, at de 100 Spdl., <lb/>
som Hs Majestæt Kongen naadigst har behaget gjennem Deres <lb/>
Excellence at skjænke til Uddeling blandt Huusarme paa Højstsalig <lb/>
Kong Carl Johans Fødselsdag den 26de January 1848, <lb/>
ere fordeelte saaledes:</p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>til de 8 Lemmer, der have Plads paa Kong Carl <lb/>
    Johans Forsørgelsesanstalt i Vaterland . . . . . . . . . .</cell>
                     <cell>4 Spdr</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>til 23 trængende Familier 22 Favne Brænde . . . . .</cell>
                     <cell>48  "</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>til Beklædning af 24 Børn . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="underline">  48  "  </hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>					tilsammen</cell>
                     <cell>100 Spdr.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Administrationen for Understøttelsesselskabet i <placeName>Christiania</placeName>
                     <lb/>
                     <date>den 26de January 1848</date>.</dateline>
                  <lb/>
                  <signed>Hedvig Mariboe  Constance Spørck  Hanna Lorch  Christ. Rennesen<lb/>
    	  Emilie Blich		Christina Berg <lb/>
A.H. Thangen  Schiøtt  Joh. Heiberg  Peter Schreiner</signed>
                  <lb/>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="vedlegg">
               <head type="tillegg">
                  <supplied resp="editor">Tillegg til rapport av 6. februar 1848</supplied>
               </head>
               <head type="sub2">
                  <hi rend="underline">Copy</hi>.</head>
               <opener>To the Commissioners appointed by His Majesty the King, to investigate <lb/>
the project of a Railway to connect Christiania with the Lakes Øiern<lb/>
    	  and Mjøsen. <lb/>
                  <salute>Gentlemen.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>	I beg to acknawledge the receipt of your Report of the 22nd <lb/>
September 1847 and to inform you that the result thereof is highly <lb/>
satisfactory to me. It appears to me that your estimate af £ 50,000 for <lb/>
the gross annual revenue to be derived from the working of this Railway <lb/>
has been produced by moderate calculations of the increase to be expected <lb/>
over the present actual traffic and I cannot doubt that this increase <lb/>
will eventually be still greater because my experience of the effect of <lb/>
Railways even in this Country (where the transition has been made from <lb/>
the best stone Roads to the present Iron-Roads) would fully warrant this <lb/>
belief, how much more then will the circumstances in the case under <lb/>
consideration justify me in holding out this prospect when the transition <lb/>
will take place from the worst kind of Road to the best kind assisted <lb/>
by the now well developed power of the Locomotive Engine.</p>
               <p>	How undeniable this result may appear to the few thoroughly <lb/>
conversant with the subject, yet it must be borne in mind, that to the many <lb/>
much uncertainty will exist, as to the capabilities of an untried Country <lb/>
(with peculiar physical difficulties to grapple with) to develope <lb/>
that further increase beyond the quantity estimated by the Commission.</p>
               <p>	Taking then your Estimate of £ 50,000 as the gross annual Revenue <lb/>
for the first three years after the opening of the Line and deducting <lb/>
50 per cent therefrom for the working expences £ 25,000 will be left as <lb/>
the nett revenue for a Dividend.</p>
               <p>	Now in the present and probable future state of the money market <lb/>
for the next three years with the surplus available Capital of this <lb/>
Country in full demand for the construction of Railway Works at home. <lb/>
It cannot be expected that Capitalists here will be induced to invest <lb/>
in a foreign Country without a well founded prospect of realizing from <lb/>
8 to 10 per cent; the rate of interest now paid for money raised for <lb/>
Railway Undertakings in this Country being 7 per cent for the next two  <lb/>
years.</p>
               <p>	From a careful weighing and collating \of/ the data collected by <lb/>
Mr England in Norway, with my own experience of the cost of Works out <lb/>
of this Country, I have arrived at the conclusion that the total cost <lb/>
for a single Line of way from Christiania to Mjøsen will not exceed <lb/>
£ 420,000, this sum to include Land, Stations and working Stock. Now in <lb/>
order that the Proprietors may have a tolerable certainty of a nett <lb/>
return of 8 to 10 per cent this sum of 420,000 must be reduced to 270,000 <lb/>
having 150,000 to be raised by other means.</p>
               <p>	Taking into consideration the immense advantages which will accrue <lb/>
to the Metropolis and the Country generally by the making of this Railway <lb/>
I think it very reasonable that the Government should advance this <lb/>
sum of £ 150,000 on the following conditions, namely</p>
               <p>	That the private Shareholders in Norway and England should have a <lb/>
preference dividend to the amount of 8 per cent on their Capital Stock; <lb/>
that then any surplus shall be set aside for interest on the Government <lb/>
Stock to the extent of 4 per cent, from which point any further nett <lb/>
proceeds shall be divided in proportion to the Stock of either party.</p>
               <p>	The well known system adopted by the French Government of advancing <lb/>
the money for the Land and lower-Works of their Lines will afford ample <lb/>
precedent for the Norwegian Government in this case.</p>
               <p>	In making the above propositions I beg the Commission wil not consider <lb/>
me pledged to them as definitive, but will be pleased to construe <lb/>
them in the light of an arrangement which in my belief will meet the <lb/>
view of Capitalists on this side as a basis for negociation with the <lb/>
Government for the concession of the proposed Line.</p>
               <p>	Having thus disposed of the great leading question of the ways and <lb/>
means of raising the Capital I will proceed to consider a few further <lb/>
details.</p>
               <p>	After a due examination of the Plans and Sections submitted to me <lb/>
I approve of the Line as laid down thereon; and with respect to the  <lb/>
alternative Lines at the Termini I adopt the yellow Line from the  <lb/>
Bordtompter at Christiania running south of Galgeberg to Bryn-dam which <lb/>
being an inclined plane of 1 in 40 I purpose working by the through <lb/>
Locomotive Engine, here assisted by such mechanical means as have been for <lb/>
some time in use in this Country; the increase of cost of construction <lb/>
in this yellow Line over the Red Line by North of Tøien will be about <lb/>
£ 6,000. Of the alternatives at Eidsvold - Bakken I think the ballance <lb/>
of Evidence is in favor of the Sundgaarden Terminus provided there be <lb/>
no difficulties thrown in the way as regards the navigation of the Wormen <lb/>
River, but whether this or the Baadshaug site be ultimately chosen <lb/>
(the comparative cost being much the same) I have no doubt that Eidsvold - <lb/>
Bakken should be the present Terminus of the Railway and that the <lb/>
route laid down to reach this point is the best the country affords.</p>
               <p>	With regard to the effects to be anticipated from the action of <lb/>
"Telle" and the accumulation of Snow in working the Line I have come <lb/>
to the conclusion that the cheapness of Timber and Timber labour combined <lb/>
with thorough Drainage will enable us effectually to master these <lb/>
difficulties within the limits of the foregoing Estimate,</p>
               <p>	It has been heretofore suggested that the Section between Christiania <lb/>
and Moe should be carried out first and the result ascertained before <lb/>
anything be done on the remaining Section from Moe to Eidsvold - <lb/>
Bakken. This mode may be found expedient as regards raising the Capital; <lb/>
but the traffic results to be obtained by this Experiment will give no <lb/>
just idea of what may be expected by the completion of the entire scheme <lb/>
to the Mjøsen. My Estimate for this first Section a distance of 19 miles <lb/>
is £ 220.000.</p>
               <p>	With respect to the copy of the form of the proposed concession to <lb/>
the Brittish Consul General for Norway I must object to the Clause d, <lb/>
which compels the future Company to pay duty on the materials imported <lb/>
for the Construction of the Railroad; with this Clause expunged, and an <lb/>
alteration of the time allowed for making a beginning after the concession <lb/>
be made, I can advise English Capitalists to accede to its terms.</p>
               <p>	I cannot conclude this Report without paying a well merited compliment <lb/>
to Lieut. Ræder for the manner in which he has got up the Plans <lb/>
and allow me to take this opportunity of thanking him for the very able <lb/>
assistance he has rendered throughout this affair.</p>
               <p>	I also affords me the greatest pleasure to find that my representative <lb/>
Mr England has not only secured your good wishes, but that he has <lb/>
excecuted the task I assigned him with great accuracy and ability so as <lb/>
fully to justify the confidence I placed in him</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>I am Gentlemen<lb/>
    		  your obedient Servant</salute>
                  <lb/>
                  <signed>
                     <persName>Rob. Stephenson</persName>
                  </signed>
                  <lb/>
                  <dateline>
                     <placeName>London,</placeName>
                     <date>12 January 1848</date>.</dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
